A Guide to the Wilson Family Papers, 1693-1866
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Wilson Family Papers, 1693-1866
The Library of Virginia
22069
10 leaves and 45 pages
Wilson Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Indiana C. Young of Norfolk, Virginia, by I. B. Wilson, October 1942.
Biographical Information
The Wilson family settled in Norfolk County, Virginia, and Currituck County, North Carolina, becoming prominent landowners in each county during the 18th and 19th centuries. James Wilson, Sr., (d. 1756) was a major in the militia and served as sheriff and magistrate of Norfolk County. James Wilson, Sr., (1742-1820) and Tatum Wilson (d. 1795) were brothers. Caleb Wilson (1771-1835) was the son of James Wilson.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1693-1866, of the Wilson family of Norfolk County, Virginia, consisting of deeds and abstracts of deeds for property in Norfolk County in Norfolk, Virginia, and in Currituck County, North Carolina; a deed for a slave woman; land grants for land in Norfolk County; surveys of property in Norfolk County; plats for "Little Cumberlin," the "Long Ridge," and "The Deading;" and wills and abstracts of wills for Henry Butt, George Burgess, Isaac Davis, and members of the Wilson family. Papers also include a decree and abstract of decree in the suit of Caleb Wilson, et. al., vs Nathaniel Wilson, et. al., issued by the Superior Court of Chancery in Williamsburg, Virginia; bill of complaint against James T. Wilson, et. al., by John W. Young to the Norfolk County Circuit Court; and a bond from Simon Wilson to James Wilson.
Contents List
- Abstract of deed, 9 November 1693, for 150 acres [in Norfolk County?] from Henry Butt (d. 1711) to William Suggs (d. 1708), both of Norfolk County.
- Extract of the will, recorded 18 May 1711, of Henry Butt of Norfolk County.
- Extract of the will, recorded 19 June 1724, of George Burgess (d. 1724) of Norfolk County.
- Will, 28 May 1754, of Caleb Wilson (d. ca. 1754) of Currituck County, North Carolina.
- Will, dated 13 January 1749/50 and proved May 1756, of James Wilson, Sr. (d. 1756), of Norfolk County.
- Deeds of lease and release, 16-17 July 1760, for 40 acres in Norfolk County from Simon Wilson (d. 1801) to Malachi Wilson, Jr. (d. 1794), both of Norfolk County.
- Deed, dated 7 February 1785 and recorded March 1785, for 50 acres in Currituck County from Tatum (d. 1795) and Charity Wilson (d. 1797) to Jonathan Barnes, all of Currituck County.
- Land grant, 27 July 1787, for 160 acres in Norfolk County from Lieutenant Governor Beverley Randolph (1754-1797) to James Wilson, Sr. (1742-1820), and Charles Wilson of Norfolk County.
- Will, 14 October 1794, of Josiah Wilson (d. 1795) of Norfolk County.
- Will, dated 14 October 1794 and recorded 20 July 1795, of Josiah Wilson (d. 1795) of Norfolk County.
- Will, 12 February 1803, of Isaac Davis (1809) of Norfolk County.
- Deed, dated 6 May 1803 and recorded 16 May 1803, for 150 acres in Norfolk County from James Wilson, Sr., to Caleb Wilson (1771-1835), both of Norfolk County.
- Land grant, 13 May 1805, for 584 acres in Norfolk County from Governor John Page (1744-1808) to Caleb Wilson.
- Deed, 1 June 1810, for a female slave from Zack Jordan of Robeson County, North Carolina to Caleb Wilson.
- Deed, dated 26 October 1819 and recorded 6 November 1819, for a lot in Borough of Norfolk from Anthony Walke (1778-1820) and Edwin Walke, executors of Anthony Walke (d. 1814), all of Princess Anne County, to Caleb Wilson.
- Will, dated 27 September 1817 and recorded 19 December 1820, of James Wilson, Sr. of Norfolk County.
- Extract of decree, 16 July 1821, from Superior Court of Chancery in Williamsburg, Virginia, in suit of Caleb Wilson, et al., against Nathaniel Wilson, et al.
- Decree, 16 July 1821, from Superior Court of Chancery in Williamsburg, Virginia, in suit of Caleb Wilson, et al., against Nathaniel Wilson, et al.
- Bearings of survey, 1850, of Hickory Ground Farm by James W. Nicholls.
- Survey, 8 August 1854, of 121 acres in Norfolk County for John W. Young by Richard Wash.
- Two surveys, 10 March 1866, for John W. Young and James Fisk (ca. 1829-1890) by John F. Cooper, all of Norfolk County.
- Bond, dated January 17--, from Simon Wilson of Norfolk County to James Wilson of Princess Anne County.
- Bill of complaint, no date, of James T. Wilson (1806-1880), Charles W. Wilson, and Walter H. Wilson (1851-1913) by John W. Young all of Norfolk to George Blow (1813-1894), judge of the Norfolk County Circuit Court.
- Plat, no date, of "Little Cumberlin."
- Plat, no date, of "The Long Ridge."
- Plat, no date, of "Patent for the Deading."